/*jshint esversion: 6 */
/* Quiz questions */
const data = [{
        question: "Which is the Arduino Board with most number of Pins?",
        a: 'Arduino Nano',
        b: 'Arduino Lillypad',
        c: 'Arduino Mega 2560',
        d: 'Arduino MKR 1000',
        correct: 'c',
    },
    {
        question: "How to get analog values from an analog pins?",
        a: 'analogWrite()',
        b: 'analogRead()',
        c: 'digitalRead()',
        d: 'Serial.read()',
        correct: 'b',
    },
    {
        question: "From which language was the Arduino Programming Language derived from?",
        a: 'Python',
        b: 'C/C++',
        c: 'Java',
        d: 'Swift',
        correct: 'b',
    },
    {
        question: "Which type of pins can be used to control Servo Motors?",
        a: 'All Digital Pins',
        b: 'UART Pins',
        c: 'Digital Pins with PWM Out',
        d: 'Analog Pins',
        correct: 'c',
    },
    {
        question: "An output is something that happens when a circuit is in use.  An example of an output is:",
        a: 'Light flashing',
        b: 'Buzzer sounding',
        c: 'Temperature being given',
        d: 'All of the answers are correct',
        correct: 'd',
    },
    {
        question: "In the case of Arduino UNO, which pin is connected internally to the onboard LED?",
        a: 'Pin 10',
        b: 'Pin 6',
        c: 'Pin 11',
        d: 'Pin 13',
        correct: 'd',
    },
    {
        question: "What is the value of Crystal Oscillator in Arduino UNO?",
        a: '1024 Khz',
        b: '4 MHz',
        c: '700 Mhz',
        d: '16 Mhz',
        correct: 'd',
    },
    {
        question: "What are Arduino “Shields”?",
        a: 'Shields are water/fire resistant ceramic coating for Arduino',
        b: 'A Hard covering held by straps or a handle attached on one side, used as a protection against blows or physical stress.',
        c: 'Specialized boards with a particular function where you can connect your Arduino.',
        d: 'Shields are protective covers to prevent Arduino from physical damage.',
        correct: 'c',
    },
    {
        question: "What are the two basics functions used while programming an Arduino Board?",
        a: 'delay() & start()',
        b: 'loop() & setup()',
        c: 'start() & finish()',
        d: 'digitalread() & analogread()',
        correct: 'b',
    },
    {
        question: "What is the full form of GPIO ?",
        a: 'General Practice Internal Operator',
        b: 'Grand Programmer Initial Order',
        c: 'General Purpose Input Output',
        d: 'General Purpose Internal Object',
        correct: 'c',
    },
];
const homeRef = document.querySelector('#home');
const playerNameRef = document.querySelector('#playername');
const quizRulesRef = document.querySelector('#quiz-rules');
const quizStartButtonRef = document.querySelector('#quiz-start');
const displayQuestionNumberRef = document.querySelector('#question-number');
const quizSummaryRef = document.querySelector('#summary');
const quizResultsRef = document.querySelector('#quiz-summary');
const quizRef = document.querySelector('#quiz');
const answerRef = document.querySelectorAll('.answer');
const questionRef = document.querySelector('#question');
const optionARef = document.querySelector('#option-a');
const optionBRef = document.querySelector('#option-b');
const optionCRef = document.querySelector('#option-c');
const optionDRef = document.querySelector('#option-d');
const submitBtnRef = document.querySelector('#submit');
const quizCompletionInfo = document.querySelector('#quiz-completion');
const form = document.querySelector('#playername-form');

/* Variables to track quiz progress */

let questionNumber = 1;
let currentQuiz = 0;
let score = 0;
let correctAnswers = 0;
let incorrectAnswers = 0;

/* Set array with randomized questions for each quiz - question will not be displayed in the same sequence as in previous quiz*/

let randomArrayItems = shuffleArray(data);

/* Add event listener to the form submit button */

form.addEventListener('submit', function (event) {
    console.log(event);
    homeRef.style.display = 'none';
    quizRulesRef.classList.remove('hide-content');
    document.querySelector('#player').innerHTML = "Hi " + playerNameRef.value;
    console.log('Username', playerNameRef.value);
    event.preventDefault();
});

/* Add event listener to the submit button to start quiz */

quizStartButtonRef.addEventListener('click', function () {
    quizRulesRef.classList.add('hide-content');
    quizRef.classList.remove('hide-content');
});

loadQuiz();

function loadQuiz() {
    deselectAnswers();
    const currentQuizData = randomArrayItems[currentQuiz];
    questionRef.innerText = currentQuizData.question;
    optionARef.innerText = currentQuizData.a;
    optionBRef.innerText = currentQuizData.b;
    optionCRef.innerText = currentQuizData.c;
    optionDRef.innerText = currentQuizData.d;
    displayQuestionNumberRef.innerHTML = `<h1>Question ${questionNumber} of ${data.length}</h1>`;
}

/* credit to https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LxQK4F0xwmU to randomize array elements*/

function shuffleArray(arrayToShuffle) {
    for (let i = arrayToShuffle.length - 1; i > 0; i--) {
        let randomPosition = Math.floor(Math.random() * (i + 1));
        let temp = arrayToShuffle[i];
        arrayToShuffle[i] = arrayToShuffle[randomPosition];
        arrayToShuffle[randomPosition] = temp;
    }
    return arrayToShuffle;
}

/*Function to deselect all answers after the question is being displayed*/

function deselectAnswers() {
    answerRef.forEach((answerEl) => (
        answerEl.checked = false));
}

/* Function to select answer */

function getSelected() {
    let answer;
    answerRef.forEach((answerEl) => {
        if (answerEl.checked) {
            answer = answerEl.id;
            console.log(answer);
        }
    });
    return answer;
}

submitBtnRef.addEventListener("click", () => {
    const answer = getSelected();
    if (answer) {
        if (answer === data[currentQuiz].correct) {
            score++;
            correctAnswers++;
        } else {
            incorrectAnswers++;
        }
        currentQuiz++;
        questionNumber++;
        updateQuizStatistics();
        if (currentQuiz < data.length) {
            loadQuiz();
        } else {
            quizSummaryRef.classList.remove('hide-content');
            quizRef.classList.add('hide-content');
            if (score == 0) {
                quizCompletionInfo.innerHTML = `Ups..`;
                quizResultsRef.innerHTML = `
          <h2>None of the questions were answered correctly.</h2>
<button onclick = "location.reload()">Try again</button>
          `;
            } else {
                quizResultsRef.innerHTML = `
          <h2>You have answered ${score} of ${data.length} questions correctly.</h2>
<button onclick = "location.reload()">Try again</button>
          `;
            }
        }
    }
});

/* Function to update information about correctly or incorrectly answered question */

function updateQuizStatistics() {
    document.querySelector('#correct-answers').innerHTML = correctAnswers;
    document.querySelector('#correct-answers').style.color = "green";
    document.querySelector('#incorrect-answers').innerHTML = incorrectAnswers;
    document.querySelector('#incorrect-answers').style.color = "Red";
}